software engineering radio episode 1
patterns
[Music]
welcome to this first official episode
of software engineering radio in this
episode
Marcus Volta and Mejia shall talk about
patterns patterns are a very important
topic in software engineering it's
become widely known through the Goff
book design patterns however in this
episode we also talk about patterns that
go beyond what the Goff book describes
what are the like the top three examples
you could give on on patterns I think
that the most used and most well-known
pattern is probably the observer pattern
where one object notifies a set of other
objects of changes so for example if you
have some graphical application where
several views have to reflect the
changes of some data structure then
whenever the data structure changes the
data structure notifies the various view
objects of the change and they can then
query the tank to change data and then
change the view accordingly another
well-known pattern is probably the proxy
it's used all over the place in remoting
systems so instead of talking to an
object directly which you obviously
can't do if it's located on a remote
machine you talk to a local object that
looks the same as the remote one and the
local one the proxy forwards all the
calls to the remote one through
networking or other means and another
one is the reactor which I think it's
better if you explain Michael yeah
director basically decouples
demultiplexing and dispatching of events
for example networks Network events from
the application specific logic to handle
events so you have two reactor on the
one side and you have application
specific handlers that you register with
a reactor and whenever the registered
event occurs the handlers invoked and
reacts on it so it's mainly used for
building scalable multi-threaded systems
or yeah not actually multi-threaded
reactor actually can serve well too
design single thread third application
single threaded scalable applications
and but you can also work with it in a
multi-threaded environment but then you
also need other patterns like the leader
follower pattern to cope with the
concurrency okay so before we go into
too much detail I think we'll explain
one or two patterns in detail later
maybe we should talk a little bit about
the history of patterns when did it all
start I thought like what Cunningham was
the first person to talk about it yeah
what Cunningham and Ken back
they started in 1987 with the
documentation of I believe it was very 5
user interface patterns that they
documented at sea to calm and with that
it all began they started to do
publications about it and in in the
1990s ken bag actually wrote his
dissertation in the 1990s Erich gamma
wrote his dissertation on patterns which
in later resulted in 1995 in the
well-known design patterns book by Erich
gamma rich at Elm rough Johnson and Sean
visitas the the golf gang of four it's
funny because I think most people think
that that the golf book was actually the
first patterns thing in the IT world but
that wasn't actually the case yeah
soon after golf then the pattern
oriented software architecture track
started by Bush Monstar and wenyan
Ranaut started current it's mostly
referred simply as poser wand okay and
is there a difference between the
patterns in the golf book and in the
poster book I mean the golf patterns are
known as the classical design patterns
what's the content of the poster
wonderful poster one book is more about
architecture patterns sometimes also
referred to as architectural styles ok
so before we discuss more about the
content of certain specific patterns
I think we should look a little bit at
the form of pattern so patterns are
documented in a very specific way
actually there are several ways if you
look at the Goff book the original
design patterns Bowflex gamma and the
others they basically have I think it's
11 sections for each pattern right yeah
yeah and the most important ones are
certainly the contacts the problem and
the solution so if you want to define
what a pattern is people say a pattern
is a problem in a certain context with a
specific solution and that that problem
is usually well known so documenting a
pattern only makes sense if the problem
that it solves is actually encountered
by many people in different solution and
in maybe even different different
technical contexts so the context
section of a pattern describes here the
environment the situation in which you
typically are software-wise
when the problem arises that you then
describe as the second part and then of
course you show the solution that helps
you solve the problem in that specific
context another important section is the
forces you can only solve a problem in a
specific way if you know what you have
to take into account when solving it
like for example system should be should
should run fast or it shouldn't should
consume only as little memory as
possible or things like that so when
describing the problem in the pattern
you always have to add a number of
forces that guide you when finding out
the solution and this basically comes
down to a kind of reusable piece of
knowledge that other people can read or
listen to and then use in their own in
their own environments in their own
software matters in this context I often
heard also the term resulting context so
what exactly is in the resulting context
of a pattern yeah so if you describe the
solution of a pattern and this solution
solves the problem taking into account
the forces into in a specific way then
after you you you implement it or you
decided for a specific solution then you
have consequences you you know that okay
so solving
this problem this or that way makes the
system quite fast or slow or small or
scalable or whatever and once you are
there you can then describe kind of new
problems that arise from having used
that pattern and that basically opens
the road to several other patterns that
might follow the current one it
following the sense of if you have
implemented this one then you might want
to consider also implementing other ones
because the resulting context recommends
using other patterns so this is
especially interesting in pattern
languages and pattern sequences I think
we discussed that later okay and then I
also learned there is Alexandrian form
there's a golf forum pauza
has it's our own form then there is the
Portland forum so what is the key
difference between those forms and why
why are there multiple forms okay so I
think the community agrees that a
pattern is always as I said before
there's this problem in a specific
context with a well working solution
however there are different kinds of
patterns we will see that later and
different kinds of patterns can be
described in different we are literal
forums better so for example if you have
a very technical pattern software design
then the golf forum is probably very
useful because it also includes sections
such as structure where you then usually
add a class diagram or something like
that you have a section interactions
where you use sequence diagrams or
something like that to show how the
dynamic collaboration between the
various participants of the pattern is
actually set up and so on however if you
for example describe I don't know
organizational patterns we'll talk about
that in a couple of minutes then this
these organizational patterns can't be
described necessarily with those
technical terms and diagrams and
structure and interactions so there are
other pattern forms that are very more
useful for this kind of pattern so if we
talk about the Alexandrian form this is
interesting because it's the original
form used by somebody called Christopher
Alexander he was a or he is a building
architect
nothing with software and so he
originally originally invented the the
form of using patterns to describe stuff
he wrote a book called a pattern
language which contains a thing 253
mature patterns organized into a pattern
language that helped people design good
cities and good buildings and good
living rooms and these kinds of things
and he used a specific forum they had a
little very little structure so it
didn't have these 11 subheadings it was
more like four or five sections so it
was context problem with forces solution
resulting context and then an example if
I remember it correctly and so this is a
very good form that can be used if you
describe non-technical things also you
can also describe technical things like
we used it in our book for the
describing remoting infrastructures so
the the gov form golf stands for Gang of
Four basically starts with a heading and
then small section maybe one or two
sentences that abstracts the purpose of
the pattern then we go on explaining the
motivation that's typically an example
situation in which you want to use the
pattern then the next section is the
so-called applicability where in general
terms in which a situation the pattern
is useful and then funny thing is there
is actually no real solution part it
doesn't say solution anywhere it just
goes on and explains the structure of
the solution then it explains the
various participants for example in
context of the observer give the subject
the thing that changes and the observers
those that want to be notified about the
change of a subject then you have the
interactions which look at the structure
from a more than having point of view
and show how the library's participants
interact consequences and then an
important section especially for low
level design or coding patterns
implementation you can usually implement
a pattern in various ways things change
or vary in in detail and the
implementation share section shows you
step by step how to implement a pattern
and also if there are variations in
implementations shows them
the next section is then even more
example code
this usually connects to the
introductory motivation and then very
important in all pattern descriptions is
known uses a pattern is not something
you invent it's something you dig out
from existing systems so in order to
kind of prove that what you described is
actually a well known and well used
solution for the problem you will list
and explain known uses and then finally
the Goff pattern form finishes with a
number of related patterns to kind of
give you a road map through the books or
collections of patterns so Michael why
don't you explain a bit more about the
poster form the poster form is another
form it has been used in the past three
post our volumes and so I'm all tightly
related more closely related to the
poser
books so and maybe because of that I
like the poster form or the poser form
has an explicit solution section and it
explicitly marks and lists the forces
which I think is very valuable to know
what kind of trade-offs I the pattern is
suggesting what what kind of trade-offs
I have to consider and also it has an
extra set very answer section where
certain variations from the core of the
pattern our documented and so instead of
just having than a separate pattern for
it you can cover the variance in the
variance section besides that there's
much in common to intend is the context
here and in the powder form that's it so
maybe then let's move on to to discuss
some of the misconceptions about
patterns I think there are a couple that
that it's worth pointing out you do you
want to start with the blueprint thing
yeah
very often I hear that patterns are
regarded as UML blueprints as that the
pattern always has to have the same
implementation class structure you know
and
patterns are only about object
orientation and that's not true you can
apply patterns also to other systems and
also to non object-oriented ways of
solving ways of programming in though it
best matches with object orientation so
yeah in some case tools computer-aided
software engineering or today it's
called model driven software development
tools it's also called blueprints and
that there are patterns but you have to
be careful what that I let you iterate
on it Marcus yeah because this is really
something where I have a really explicit
opinion about so you know in those model
driven tools they're usually talking
about automatically implementing
patterns and and this is to some extent
kind of nonsense on the one hand of
course if you decided that you want to
use a certain pattern in a certain
situation then you can let your
generator your code generator your case
tool your MDA tool your whatever you can
make sure that the tool actually
generates the respective code to to
implement the pattern in the code it
generates however reducing patterns to
something that's automated in such tools
is probably really a bad idea because
parents are basically documentation they
have a lot of aspects several aspects
that cannot be automated things like the
the forces I mean the decision that
guides you through whether it's useful
to use the pattern and which variant and
why and how it's not something you can
easily automate in tools it's it's
probably a good thing
to keep the term pattern separate from
automating certain code transformations
and tools they're probably better called
templates of course if you if you have
templates that implement the observer
pattern then it's useful to say that
your code generator uses the observer
pattern internally but saying that the
patterns are basically automated through
the tool in
you don't have to understand the
patterns just use the tool that's that's
nonsense
yeah another common misconception is
that patterns are innovations and that's
really they are the opposite patterns
are best practices patterns have to
multiple known uses of existing systems
or having known users means I'm not
innovative anymore
but still they're very valuable for
documenting and communicating best
practices and for example for new
problem domain for example for
aspect-oriented software development you
just have 10 to start mine patterns from
experience from scratch there are no
patterns and people who would claim that
I don't believe it has to ripe the
domain people have to learn they have to
have experience and then they were
together derive patterns from it so this
probably means that most parents are not
written by university personnel and
researchers who have to write papers
about new things but rather our parents
are probably written by practitioners
and folks from industry right right ok
which is good for a change so maybe
let's look at some of the domains that
are covered with with patterns I think
most people know the Gough book so it's
basically most people know design
patterns patterns that help you make
your object or entity science better so
but I think we agree that that that it's
not I mean this is the bare minimum that
people have to know about patterns and I
think everybody really knows them but
maybe let's talk about some more not so
well-known domains in which patterns
have been used do you want to start yeah
well the closest one is the domain of
software architecture and poles are one
is definitely one of the examples in
that area but there's also like user
interface design user interaction
patterns testing patterns for example
those by a
for long a and Kyle Brown their teaching
patterns Marcus could you explain
something about those yeah the idea was
to collect best practices and patterns
in the context of teaching so describing
how to efficiently design courseware how
to run classes and so on and there have
been there has been a big community that
called the pedagogical patterns project
recently it hasn't been very active but
there are very interesting patterns
written in this area so if you if you're
a person who works with teaching and and
designs classes it's really worth
looking at it there should be a website
called the Pedigo with www had a got to
go parents project not sure whether it's
still online but certainly worth a try
also at my own home page at photo da you
can find some pedagogical patterns and
links to other ones cool so the next
area is like documentation there is the
a child documentation and patterns book
by Andrea swooping there's the
organizational whole area lately covered
by James Kaplan and Neil Harrison and
also Linda rice saying they had a book
on it I believe the title was fearless
change definitely worth reading and you
can learn a lot from it
there is also patterns of books that
describe pattern languages for various
middleware and infrastructure things
like remoting and components but I think
we'll discuss those aspects in a later
episode so we won't go into detail here
right right I think something we should
talk about is the way how parents come
about and since since patterns are yeah
as we said before mined from from the
experience of a community there is also
a very well working community that helps
parent authors to refine them so maybe
let's talk a couple of minutes about the
plop
conference series and how those
conferences work I think that's that's
fun yeah so plop stands for pattern
languages of programming and they got
initiated in in the early 1990s I
believe in 1994 was the first one and
yeah those conferences are have a very
typical form they're their own form of
running the conferences and the key
events in at those conferences are the
writers workshops and Marcus could you
explain what a Writers Workshop is yes
so the idea in in parents conferences is
not that people come there and you know
present their work to a tour to audience
that sits there and listens and and
looks at the Guru presenting stuff
rather the petros conferences are
authors conferences so authors go there
to present their work yes but then get
feedback so the first step in those
conferences is what is called
shepherding so you you submit your paper
and then you're assigned and experience
patterns author who gives you very very
very detailed feedback on the pattern
this is a process that goes about two
months or something usually two to four
iterations and as a result your pattern
should be much better from a Content
perspective but also from a structure
and language perspective then your
original submission so the next step
then is you go to the conference
everybody meets has a lot of fun and in
the writers workshops there is usually a
group of maybe six to twelve people who
basically sit in a circle usually you as
the author don't say much you sit there
listen to the discussion of your
colleagues who discuss your pattern so
they talk about what they like in the
pattern and so you're kind of confirmed
that certain things have been a good
idea they also tell you what should be
improved in the pattern so after usually
half an hour of listening to them you
should get a lot of additional
inspiration of how to improve your
pattern so as a consequence after
patterns have gone through such a
writer's work
they're usually much better at least
from a readability perspective than the
original submission and this helps to
keep the quality of patterns
publications okay and the original blob
conference is the one in the United
States in Illinois it's the plop
conference but there are also variations
and and derivations in Europe for
example in Germany and Scandinavia and
also in South Africa not to list all the
club conferences so it's probably worth
pointing out that if you're interested
in in patterns a bit deeper than kind of
just using the design patterns then it's
probably a good starting point to go to
one of those conference even if you
don't have a paper because it helps you
get in touch with the community and and
all the the process and and all these
kinds of things
also of course it's more fun to go there
if you have a paper a good link to check
out as Hillside net the hillside groove
is basically the common basis of the
pattern community you find all the
information and follow on links about
the community the patterns books that
have been written just almost everything
about patterns okay so we've talked
about patterns a long time now in this
in this episode previously I think we
mentioned the term pattern language I
think we should explore a little bit
what kind of other kinds of header like
literature there exists you want to
start yeah so part one actually started
with the term system of patterns and
that is patterns that have a loose
relation to each other which is
basically yeah a catalog is also
sometimes the term used for it a catalog
of patterns which has no tight
connection to it then there is the term
a pattern compound for example the
bureaucracy a pattern by Turk relay and
compound patterns contain other patterns
their creative combinations are their
kind of well at one point it was a
creative step yeah but then they use for
example in the case of bureaucracy they
use the composite mediator chain of
responsibility and observer pattern
internally to achieve their solution
their goal so send a good question you
take a number of existing patterns
combine them and and give it a new name
no no it's it's not like that and you
you wouldn't get through a writer's
workshop with that you must provide
additional value it must be a meaningful
and new combination of patterns that's
not just an addition of existing
patterns but there's a there's a fine
limit fine border between what's really
then acceptable as a compound pattern
and what's not okay so the next kind of
step upwards in complexity is the
pattern sequences yeah pattern sequences
our topic that is still maturing the
pattern sequence describes basically how
a system evolved what was the first
pattern that got used then the second
pattern it's it's really a stepwise
refinement of and development of your
architecture and a pattern the sequence
is basically one useful stepwise
refinement using patterns to build a
system okay and most elaborate way of
combining patterns is probably the
pattern language yeah pattern languages
combine several pattern sequences for
specific domain for example remoting so
in a domain like remoting a pattern
language documents all the
most common the most applicable patterns
with trade-offs and alternatives when
ever you selected one pattern depending
on the resulting context on the
consequences you might choose another
pattern and the pass through the pattern
language are described using pattern
sequences so that means I mean to some
extent it sounds quite esoteric and not
not very useful but but if you if you
look at some of the books published in
that area they really give you a
hands-on guide through potentially quite
complex topics like for example remoting
they start with explaining you know
things like proxy and marshaling and
then talk about how you manage the
lifecycle of those remote objects talk
about asynchronous communication and so
on and so on
so they're really very very useful if
you want to understand certain domains a
bit deeper than just understanding the
API of CORBA or something like that so I
think this brings us to our next topic
which is basically the advantages of
patterns why why would you why would you
care I mean why are patterns important I
think primarily patterns are a good idea
because they allow you to better
communicate software software is
something that you can't touch obviously
and so talking about the internal
structure and the design reasonings has
always been hard without patterns with
patterns we have a means a common
language basically to talk about
software its structure its design and
everything around it the second thing is
reuse we share experience we share best
practices and yeah to a certain extent
you've evolved the field of software
development there's also the high goal
of a software handbook a software
architecture handbook several times
tried never really achieved yet but
hopefully endurance yeah a most current
one is this Grady Booch is approach
right right but hopefully we'll succeed
as a community in the future because I
something like that could be really
valuable to to really mature software
development to an engineering domain to
make the bit more structure into it and
to achieve the engineering aspect of
software engineering important since
we're soft engineering radio the other
thing I believe it really helped me
structure my thoughts
it helped me structure the way I work
the way I act doing software development
so the strong focus on structure helped
me also in writing go to requirement
specs because I knew when I later I have
to design my system I what I have to
rely on what what I need to make good
design decisions yeah so if you if you
have read a lot of patterns and maybe
even wrote some patterns then you kind
of naturally think in these chunks of
knowledge called patterns right so if
you have to explain things or write
things down or build a system or
whatever you have to do you kind of
naturally start thinking in in patterns
and you you think you have a problem you
think oh you know I've heard about a
pattern that solves this problem somehow
and you open the book or serve to some
webpage and you read the details and it
really helps you structure your everyday
development work I think that's really
important
another thing that I think is is
important is actually that writing
patterns can help you understand things
so when I first read the goth book a
long time ago this really helped me to
kind of get beyond this you know object
orientation is about inheritance and
encapsulation thing so it kind of gave
me the next step of building
object-oriented systems based on the
golf book and and then when I started
writing patterns this actually was kind
of the next step because it improved my
writing style so if I today write an
article or any kind of documentation and
I have enough time to actually do it
right then this always looks a bit like
patterns so I try to explain the
one text first and then outlined this is
the problem that I'm trying to describe
order a document or that I solve with a
system that I just documented clearly
and and then I come up with a solution I
explain what the consequences are and I
motivate all that with a with a easy to
understand example so writing patterns
is not just useful you know to get the
ticket to ills a to go to the Europe lob
conference it really helps you improve
your writing style and that's something
that many people should do gosh gosh I
said gosh okay so explain the term gosh
is used in Writers Workshop writers
workshops to to express that you have
exactly the same opinion instead of
saying something again and again and
again you just say gosh to agree
explicitly with what the other guy said
okay
one thing before we kind of wrap up and
and and and point to some additional
resources I think it's really
interesting to point out the amount of
literature that has been created from
the parents community 50 books 50 yeah I
just looked up at Hillside of Nan and it
was like 50 to 70 books on patterns
about serious patterns box
you mean serious in the sense that they
have been workshop they have been
workshop and they adhere to the rules of
the community and not just claim their
solutions to be patterns just because
they named them patterns so so
especially a while ago it was a good
sales argument to to put the term
pattern on your book cover but to me it
seems like the community is a bit I
don't know if you haven't been to the
conferences you're not allowed to use
the term pattern it's probably a bit bit
harsh but to some extent people expect
that patterns in a book have been
workshop that is partially on one of
those conferences right right so the
blob conferences are so to say our
quality assurance and the community
right so there is also kind of best off
so in addition to them to the
proceedings which you can get from
various sources including usually web
pages there is also a series by Edison
Wesley which is called plop D the
pattern languages of program design
series for volumes have already been
published a fifth volume should have
been published a while ago but it's it's
the publisher said it's it's in the kind
of final stages of production now
whatever that means
so far so these these plop the books
basically contain an even more refined
sentence a selection of the patterns of
the various conferences so they're yeah
kind of best off another good Lang
another contender I want to get is the
pattern Almanac by Linda rising it's now
from the year 2000 but still valid and a
good start into what kind of patterns
are available and you can use the index
in there to search for patterns that
have been documented on the problem you
currently face is there a one-stop
webpage you should go to to learn more
about pattern is there you know the
web-based patterns catalog I think it
doesn't exist no it doesn't exist yet
and as with the software architecture
hand but there many people strive to
achieve that but it's not yet there so
planned I know that it's definitely
blend and whenever it will be out there
I'm sure you can find then the link on
hillside or not ok so this I think this
concludes our our discussion about about
patterns
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio for general
information and past episodes go to WWWE
- radio dotnet SE radio wants to thank
Henning poly for providing the music we
use in this show
[Music]